<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Where, in all well-gouerned kingdomes ... care hath euer beene duly had and taken ... that breade, meats and drinkes ... to be solde ... should bee good ...</title>
            <author>City of London (England).</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06235</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16725.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1336</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22134190</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22134190</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25123</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06235)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25123)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1731:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Where, in all well-gouerned kingdomes ... care hath euer beene duly had and taken ... that breade, meats and drinkes ... to be solde ... should bee good ...</title>
                  <author>City of London (England).</author>
                  <author>Middleton, Thomas, Sir, 1550-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iaggard, printer to the honourable City of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1613]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title taken from first five lines of text.</note>
                  <note>Lord Mayor's initials, T.[homas] M.[iddleton], at head of text.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Establishes regulations for the sale of foodstuffs.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Food law and legislation --  England --  London.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25123:1"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal coat of arms</figDesc>
               <p>HONI SOIT <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>VI MAL Y PENSE</p>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.M</p>
               <p>T. M.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here, in all well-gouerned Kingdomes, Common-wealthes, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Countries, care hath euer beene duly had and taken, and commands ſtrictly giuen in publicke and in priuate, That Breade, Meats, and Drinkes of all ſorts, to be ſolde, vttered, or put to ſale, for the ſuſtenance of mankinde, ſhould bee good, ſweete, ſound, and wholeſome for mans body: And that iuſt Aſſize, Weight, &amp; Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſhould be deliuered to all perſons, vpon paines, penalties, and puniſhments, to bee inflicted vppon the Offenders, according to the qualities of their offences.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, the Right honorable Sir <hi>Thomas Middleton,</hi> Knight, Lord Maior of this the Kings Highnes City of London, &amp; his right Worſhipful Brethren the Aldermen of the ſame, conſidering the great Aſſemblie of Lords Spirituall and Temporall, &amp; Commons at this time of the high Court of Parliament, and the repayre hither of ſo many others from many parts of this realme, who are to haue their prouiſion for their dyet in a great part from this Cittie, and purpoſing as much as in them ſhall lye, duely to prouide that they bee well ſerued of Victuall, both in reſpect of the goodneſſe of the ſame, and of iuſt aſſize, weight, and meaſure, do heereby ſtraitly Charge and Command, That no Baker, Wine-ſeller, Brewer, Butcher, Poulter, Fiſhmonger, Inholder, Cooke, Alehouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, or any other Victualler, or other perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, doe at any time heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſell, vtter, or put to ſale, any Bread, Wine, Ale, Beere, Fleſh, Fiſh, or any other Victuall whatſoeuer within the ſaide City or Liberties of the ſame, but ſuch onely as ſhal be good, ſweet, ſound, and wholeſome for mans body, vppon paine of impriſonment, and ſuch further punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the qualities of their ſeuerall offences ſhall deſerue, which ſhall with all ſeuerity be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted againſt them, and euery of them.</p>
            <p>And do further heereby ſtraitly Charge and Command, That no Baker, or any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoeuer, ſhall at any time heereafter, ſell, vtter, or put to ſale, any Breade vſuallie called &amp; ſold for Wheaten bread, but that the peny loafe contain the Aſſize of xi. Ounces Troy waight at the leaſt, which is th'aſſize now appointed for the ſame, &amp; other loaues of that kind of Bread after that Rate, Nor any bread vſually called &amp; ſold for White bread, but that the peny loafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain th'Aſſize of ſeuen ounces, &amp; one quarter of an ounce troy waight at the leaſt, which is th'aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiize now appointed for the ſame, and other loaues of that kind of bread after that rate. And that no Inholder, Cooke, Tipler, Ale-houſe-keeper, or other perſon whatſoeuer, ſhall at anie time heereafter, ſell, vtter, or put to ſale, any Beere or Ale otherwiſe then by meaſures, ſealed by the Officer thereunto duely appointed. And that none of them ſell any of the beſt ſort of Ale or beere
<pb facs="tcp:25123:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>at any higher rate or price, then a penie for a full Ale quart, nor any of the ſmaller ſorte of Ale or beere at any higher rate or price, then a halfe peny for a full Ale quart.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as there hath beene verie great ſpoyle and waſte of Wheate and Barley, by reaſon of the great abuſe in brewing ſtrong and headie Beere and Ale: and beſides the abuſe in drunkenneſſe and drinking vnmeaſurably, and in ſo great exceſſe, and in exceedingly waſting of Gods bleſſinges, without care or conſcience, many poore families, men, weomen, and children, haue beene and dayly are vtterly ouerthrowne, and forced either to liue by begging, or ſterue for want, by reaſon that the inſatiable deſire of manie of the poorer ſorte of houſholders, to thoſe ſtrong Drinkes is ſuch, and their cuſtome in committing that ſin ſo grounded, as that al they can get by their labour, is hardly ſufficient to ſatiſfie their owne appetite therein, which they will (ſometimes beyond their ability) ſatiſfie, though their Wines and Children want at home.</p>
            <p>And where the vtterance of thoſe Drinkes haue beene ſo great, as Inholders, Cookes, and other Victuallers, haue had in their ſellers and other places of Store, ſome one man a hundred, ſome two hundred, and ſome three hundred barrels at one time, The ſaide Lord Maior and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen therefore, do heereby ſtraitly Charge and Command, That no Inholder, Cooke, Ale-houſe-keeper, or other Victualler whatſoeuer, ſhall at any time after publication of this Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, receiue any beere or Ale into his or her houſe, Seller, or other place, vntill all the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels of beere and Ale which he or ſhe hath, ſhall be drawne out, ſpent, and reduced to the number of twenty: and that after that time, he or ſhee, ſhal not haue, retaine, or keep in his or her houſe, ſeller, or other place, at any one time, aboue the number of twenty barrels: and that neither they nor any of them, ſhall at any time afterwarde, receiue, retaine, or keepe any beere or Ale in anie greater Veſſels then barrels onely.</p>
            <p>And where within the ſaide Citie and Liberties, many Freemen of the company of Cooks, vnder pretence of ſelling beere and ale with their meates, by colour of their Charters and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, do keepe common Alehouſes, and ſell Ale and beere both within their houſes, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſame out alſo, without ſelling any meate therewith, and are not thereunto licenſed in due forme of Law, The ſaide Lord Maior and Aldermen, doo heereby ſtraitly Charge and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, all Freemen of the ſaide Company of Cookes, That they do not at any time heereafter, directly or indirectly, ſell, vtter, or put to ſale, any beere or Ale out of their houſes, nor in theyr houſes, otherwiſe then with their meate.</p>
            <p>And where there haue beene, and dayly are vſed great deceipts in ſale of horſemeat, as well Hay and Oates, as horſe-breade within the ſayde Citie and Liberties thereof. For redreſſe and reformation therein, the ſaide Lorde Maior and Aldermen, doe heereby ſtraightlie Charge and Commaund, all Inholders, keepers of Stables and Hoaſteries, and all and euerie other perſon and perſons whatſoeuer, That neither they, nor any of them, do at any time after the publication hereof, ſell, vtter, or put to ſale, any Horſe-bread, at any other Rates and Prizes, then three Loaues Weighing one and twenty Ounces Troy waight for a penme, nor any other then ſuch as ſhall be well baked, and made of good Beanes, Branne, and woorking Meale well blended. Nor any Oates at any higher Rate or price then foure pence halfe-peny for a pecke: &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that Rate for greater and leſſer meaſures. Nor any Hay at any higher rate or price then a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of Hay weighing two pounds &amp; a halfe for a halfe-penie, and after that Rate for greater and leſſer quantitie or weight. Nor ſhall not take any more or greater price then ſixe pence day and night for Horſes, Mares, or Geldings, ſet at Liuerie within this Citie, or the Liberties there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſo after the ſame Rate.</p>
            <p>And doe alſo heereby Charge and Commaunde, all Inholders, Ale-houſe-keepers, and others, vſually receyuing lodgers, who ſhal receiue any perſon or perſons to lodge in any of their houſes, that they and euery of them, do once euery day from time to time, deliuer to the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Ward, or his Deputy, or to the Conſtable of the Precinct, where ſuch Inholder, Ale-houſekeeper, or other perſon ſhal dwel, in writing, the Names, Surnames, &amp; additions of dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place and profeſſion of ſuch perſons, as they or any of them, ſhall receiue to lodge, &amp; likewiſe of the time of their departure, to the end, the ſaide Lord Maior, and his brethren the Aldermen, may from time to time be truely informed thereof, and perſons dangerous to the King &amp; State, may the more eaſily be diſcouered.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25123:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And do heereby further Charge and commaund, That all Conſtables within the ſaide Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and the Liberties thereof, hold their Watches from nine of the Clocke in the Euening, vntill fiue of the Clocke in the Morning: and that they ſuffer no perſon to paſſe thorough anie of the Streetes or lanes of this Citie, betwixt the houres aforeſaide, vnleſſe hee or ſhee can giue good accompt of lawfull and honeſt occaſion ſo to do. And ſuch as cannot, they ſhall commit to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in one of the Compters of this Citie, or to ſome other priſon (if neede require) and certifye the Lord Maior, (or ſome other Iuſtice of peace within this Citty) thereof, the next morning. And that if the ſaide Conſtables, or any of them, vpon any ſodaine occaſion ſhall find cauſe, they ſhall make ſearch in any Inne, Victualling houſe, or other place, ſuſpected to harbour leud, looſe, ydle, or ſuſpected people: and if they ſhall finde any ſuch, they ſhall commit them to priſon, there to remaine, and certifie the ſaide Lorde Maior, or ſome other of the ſayde Iuſtices thereof, the next <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rning, to the end, ſuch order may bee taken for their punniſhment, or deliuerie as ſhall be meete.</p>
            <p>And, where the ſayde Lorde Maior, with the aduiſe of his ſaide Brethren, ſhortlie after his entrance into the Office of Maioralty of the ſayde Citie, did for the Aduancement of the honour of GOD, and for the Weale of the Kings Maieſties Subiects, Inhabitants within the ſayde Cittie, and the Liberties of the ſame, and of others repayring to the ſame from forraigne parts, giue publicke notice and warning by Proclamation of his Lordſhippes purpoſe, to endeauour and ſpeede the due execution of ſundrie Actes and Ordinances, and did thereby alſo, giue ſtraite Charge and Commaund for due Obſeruation thereof: as alſo, touching Foreſtallers and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grators, Ale-houſe-keepers, Victuallers, and others. Now, foraſmuch as there hath not been that due regarde had of the obſeruation of the ſayde Ordinances and Statutes, concerning the offences aforeſaide, nor of the ſayde publicke warning, Charge and Commaund giuen as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide, which ought to haue beene, The ſayde Lorde Maior and Aldermen, doe now therfore heereby, giue ſpeciall Charge and Commandement to al the Inqueſts of Wardmote of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the liberties thereof, and to all Conſtables, Beadles, and other Officers, and to all Informers and other perſons whatſoeuer, to whom it ſhall, or may in any wiſe appertain, that they and euerie of them, do make ſpeciall, diligent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>irefull enquiries and preſentments of al ſuch Foreſtallers, Regrators, and others: as alſo of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the other offences wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beene, or ſhall be commited againſt the true meaning of the ſaide Statutes, Actes, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, or any of them, or againſt the true meaning of any Charge or Commaund heereby gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to the end, the ſeuerall Offenders may bee duely puniſhed, and that the paines, penalties, and forfeytures may be duely leauied: wherein ſuch as ſhall be carefull and painefull to further and ſpeede due execution in this behalfe, ſhall out of the penalties and forfeytures, be (for theyr care and paines therein to be taken) ſufficiently recompenced and rewarded.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed by William Iaggard, Printer to the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Citty of London.</p>
            <closer>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> God ſaue the King. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
